"Once upon a time..."
“从前…”
"Somewhere on the Castilian plain, around 1940..."
“1940年, 卡斯蒂利亚高原的某个地方”
The movie's coming! The movie's coming!
电影来了!电影来了!
You boys are gonna fall.
好了,你会摔下来的
How are you?
- 你好吗? - 嗨
What are you doing? Get out of here!
你们干什么?走开!
Look at all the cans of film!
- 快看,电影! - 哇噢!
Let me through.
让我过去,别挡道
- What's the movie about? - The movie?
- 你什么时候放啊? 什么时候?
It's wonderful.
- 很漂亮,很漂亮的
Is it a horror movie?
- 是恐怖电影吗?
Is that all?
都是吗?
Is it a cowboy movie?
- 西部牛仔电影吗?
It's a beautiful movie.
一部很好看的电影
Are there Indians in it?
- 有印第安人吗?
It's tremendous! The best I've ever shown in this town.
很精彩! 这是我放过的最好看的电影
You can't even imagine.
将是最棒的,真的
All I can say is: ole!
这部电影…奥勒!
This evening, in the town hall,
今晚,在镇公所
at 5:00
5点钟
there'll be a special showing
将放映一部电影
of Frankenstein.
叫做“科学怪人”
Ticket prices will be
电影票价是…
one peseta for adults
大人一个银币
and two reales for children.
小孩两个里亚尔
How's it going, Tomasa?
最近过的好吗,托马斯?
I hope it's good this time.
但愿是好
It's magnificent.
很好看的,很好看
Don't start a fire, now.
现在不要生火
Careful with that brazier.
小心火盆
The film's producers do not wish to present it
影片制片人在影片放映前
without a preliminary word of caution.
想提前警告一下
This is the story of Dr. Frankenstein,
这是一个怪人的故事…
a man of science
他是一位科学家
who sought to create a living being,
他想创造生命
without recognizing that that's something only God can do.
这是只有上帝才能做的事
It's one of the strangest stories ever told.
这是一个,被搬上银幕的最怪的故事之一
It's about the great mysteries of creation.:
讲述的是创造的神秘
Iife and death.
生和死的神秘
Prepare yourselves.
各位做好准备
You may be shocked,
可能会感到震惊
or even horrified.
甚至会感到恐怖
Few films have had greater impact all over the world.
全世界很少有电影 产生这样的感想
But I would advise you
不过我劝告各位
not to take it too seriously.
不要太当真
Though nothing can bring back the happy moments we spent together,
我们一起度过的快乐时光 一去不复返了…
I pray that God grant me the joy of seeing you again.
但是向上帝祈祷也许能有幸再见到你
That's been my constant prayer
我一直都这样祈祷
ever since we parted during the war,
自从我们在战争期间 被分开之后
and it's my prayer still here in this remote spot
我还在为此祷告, 在费尔南多这个偏僻的地方
where Fernando and the girls and I try to survive.
姑娘们和我努力继续生存
Little but the walls are left of the house you once knew.
你记得吗,只剩下房子的墙
I often wonder what became of everything we had there.
我常常对我们走到 结束的事情感到奇怪
I don't say that out of nostalgia.
这不是怀旧之情…
It's hard to feel nostalgic
这些年经历了这么多事
after what we've been through these past few years.
很难有怀旧的感觉
But sometimes, when I look around me
不过有时候,当我环顾四周时
and see so much loss,
发现失去了太多东西
so much destruction and so much sadness,
太多东西被破坏了, 还有太多的悲伤
something tells me perhaps our ability to really feel life
我想…
has vanished along with all the rest.
因为这些,我们已经失去了 感觉生活的能力
I don't even know if this letter will reach you.
我不知道你是否会收到这些信
The news we get from outside
我们从外面得到的消息
is so scant and confusing.
是茫然和困惑的
Please write soon
请尽快回信
to let me know you're still alive.
这样我知道你还活着
With all my love, Teresa.
爱你的,特里萨
Sit down.
坐下
See that? He understands!
他了解我
Look at that!
快看这个!
Teresa.
特里萨?
Milagros.
米拉格罗丝!
Have you seen my wife?
有没有见到我老婆?
I think she went out a while ago.
可能出去了
- Where are the girls? - At the movie.
- 姑娘们哪去了? - 去看电影了
Is there anything to eat in the house?
有没有吃的?
I'm sure there is.
肯定有
But you should eat regular meals
你应该准时吃饭
and come down out of the clouds.
不要总抽烟
Sit down, Doctor.
坐下,博土
Try to be patient.
安静
Did you expect immediate results?
你期望快速的结果吗?
You must keep a close eye on your creature.
你得当心那个人
Listen to me. It could be dangerous.
可能是个危险人物
Dangerous? You surprise me.
危险?你让我感到惊讶
Haven't you ever wanted to take a chance?
告诉我,你从来没好奇过?
What if we never went beyond the limits of the known?
大家知道的限度背后隐藏着什么?
Have you never wished to see beyond the clouds and stars?
你从未希望了解遥远的云和星星吗?
Or to know what makes trees grow
或者了解树木生长的动力
and changes shadows to light?
和影子的变化?
But speak like this and they call you a madman.
如果你这样讲,他们会当你是疯子
Yet if I could answer just one of these questions -
不过如果我能回答其中一个问题
what eternity is, for example -
比如说什么是来世
I wouldn't care if they called me mad.
我才不会在意他们是否当我是疯子
You're young, dazed by your success.
你年轻,被自己的成功所淹没了
Wake up and see reality.
醒醒吧,看看现实
A demon whose brain -
魔鬼的头脑…
You must give it time to develop.
为自己提供进步的时间
It's a perfect brain, Doctor.
这是个完美的头脑,博士
I can tell you this now.: It came from your laboratory.
我可以告诉你, 它就来自这个实验室
The brain stolen from my laboratory
这个头脑是从我实验室偷出来
belonged to a criminal!
那就是犯罪
- Will you be long, Papa? - No, I'll just fix the wall.
- 你要很久吗,爸爸? 不会,我只是修理墙
Why don't you stay and play with me?
你干嘛不留下来跟我玩?
I have things to do, child.
我有事要做,孩子
Play with your kitten.
跟你的小猫玩吧
- Good-bye, Papa. - Good-bye.
- 再见,爸爸 - 再见…
And be good.
玩的开心点
Who are you?
你是谁啊?
I'm Maria.
我叫玛丽亚
Will you play with me?
跟我一起玩好吗?
Would you like one of my flowers?
你喜欢我的花吗?
This one's for you and this one's for me.
这是你的,这是我的
It's like a boat.
像条小船
See how they float?
看到他们漂浮的样子吗?
Get ready, Maria.
准备好,玛丽亚
I'll check the roof
我要检查屋顶
and then we'll go to the village.
然后我们就去村庄
Isabel.
伊莎贝尔…
Why did he kill her?
他干嘛杀她?
Silence!
安静!
I'll tell you later.
我待会儿告诉你
It's Frankenstein!
科学怪人!
By the sign of the holy cross
神圣的十字架
free us from our enemies,
让我们远离敌人
Lord our God.
上帝
In the name of the Father, the Son and the Holy Spirit, amen.
以圣父,圣子, 还有圣灵的名义,阿门
Where did you hide the matches?
你把火柴藏哪了?
In the drawer.
抽屉里
What?
干嘛?
Tell me what you were going to tell me.
告诉我吧
- About what? - The movie.
- 说什么? 电影啊
Not now. Tomorrow.
现在不行,明天吧
Now. You promised.
就现在,你答应了的
Why did he kill the girl,
他干嘛杀了那个女孩
and why did they kill him after that?
后来他们干嘛杀他?
You don't know. You're a liar.
你不知道,你骗人
They didn't kill him, and he didn't kill the girl.
他们没有杀他 他也没杀那个女孩
How do you know?
你怎么知道?
How do you know they didn't die?
你怎么知道他们没死?
Everything in the movies is fake.
电影里的地方都是假的
It's all a trick.
都是骗局
Besides, I've seen him alive.
而且,我看到了他
Where?
在哪?
In a place I know near the village.
我知道在村庄附近的一个地方
People can't see him.
人们看不到他
He only comes out at night.
他只在晚上出来
Is he a ghost?
他是鬼吗?
No, he's a spirit.
不,他是幽灵
Like the spirit Dona Lucia talks about?
就像露西亚小姐说的幽灵一样?
Yes, but spirits don't have bodies.
是的,但是幽灵没有肉体
That's why you can't kill them.
所以你杀不了他们
But he had one in the movie.
但他在电影里有啊
He had arms and feet.
他有手,有脚
He had everything.
什么都有
It's a disguise they put on when they go outside.
那是他们外出时,穿上的衣服
If he only comes out at night, how can you talk to him?
如果他只在晚上出来, 你怎么跟他说话啊?
I told you he was a spirit.
我说了他是幽灵
If you're his friend,
如果你是他的朋友
you can talk to him whenever you want.
就能随时都跟他说话
Just close your eyes
闭上眼睛…
and call him.
呼唤他
"It's me, Ana."
“是我,安娜.”
"Someone to whom I recently showed my glass beehive,
最近我向某人展示了我的玻璃蜂巢
with its movement like the main gear wheel of a clock-
它的机械运动就像时钟发条轮
Someone who saw the constant agitation of the honeycomb,
它的运动永不停止
the mysterious, maddened commotion
巢上的保育蜂发出……
of the nurse bees over the nests,
神秘而发狂的骚动
the teeming bridges and stairways of wax,
拥挤的桥梁和楼梯构成腊房
the invading spirals of the queen,
王后在腊房上作侵略性的螺旋
the endlessly varied and repetitive labors of the swarm,
蜂群在无尽的变化中进行重复性的劳作
the relentless yet ineffectual toil,
它们进行艰苦而又无用的苦干
the fevered comings and goings,
它们的行动是如此的狂热…
the call to sleep always ignored,
连睡觉都顾不上了
undermining the next day's work,
即使影响第二天的工作也在所不惜
the final repose of death
最后,它们终于静静地死去……
far from a place that tolerates neither sickness nor tombs -
远离了这个既不容忍疾病也不容忍死亡的地方
Someone who observed these things,
他观察着这一切
after the initial astonishment had passed,
当最初的惊讶消退后
quickly looked away
他的脸上迅速显出
with an expression of indescribable sadness and horror. "
一种难以形容的悲伤和惊骇
Two and two is four
2加2等于4
Four and two is six
4加2等于6
Six and two is eight Plus eight is 16
6加2等于8 8加8等于16
Plus eight is 24 Plus eight is 32
16加8等于24,再加8等于32
Holy souls, we kneel before you.
我向圣灵跪下
AII right. Put away your things.
很好,好了, 把自己的东西收起来
Quiet!
安静!
Or else Don Jose will get angry.
约瑟先生会生气的
Good morning, Don Jose.
早上好,约瑟先生
Poor Don Jose!
可怜的约瑟先生!
Who left him like that?
谁把他弄成这样啊?
You did, teacher!
是你,老师!
Let's see, Paulita.
我们来看看,保丽塔
What is Don Jose missing?
约瑟先生少了什么?
- His heart. - Good. Put it on him.
心脏 - 很好,加上去
Mari Carmen,
玛丽.卡门,
what's the heart for?
心脏是干什么用的?
For breathing.
呼吸
All you smarty-pants laughing so hard,
你们都很聪明,笑什么
what do we breathe with?
- 那我们用什么呼吸啊?
The lungs.
- 肺
Show them to us.
给我们看看
Put his lungs on.
把他的肺加上去
Put them on him.
放到他身上去
Very good.
很好
What is the stomach for?
胃是干什么用的?
To put food in.
装食物
Put it on him.
很好,给他装上去
Very good. Sit down.
非常好,坐下来
Now pay attention.
注意了
Don Jose can walk. He can breathe.
约瑟先生可以走路,可以呼吸
He can eat.
可以吃东西,但是..
But...
还有东西
there's still something very, very important
非常非常重要的
that's missing.
他没有
His bones.
骨骼
His ears.
- 骨骼 - 耳朵
Ana.
安娜…
You're very quiet.
你一直没出声
What is Don Jose still missing?
约瑟先生少了什么?
His eyes.
- 眼睛 - 他的…
Quiet, Isabel.
安静,伊莎贝尔
Answer when I ask you.
我没问你不要说话
- His eyes. - Very good.
- 眼睛 - 很好
Come and put them on him.
过来给他加上去
Now Don Jose can see.
约瑟先生现在有眼睛了
See the house with the well?
看到那个有井的房子吗?
- Does he Iive there? - Yes.
- 他就住在那? - 是的
You want to go there?
想过去吗?
AII right.
好啊
Isabel!
伊莎贝尔!
Mama asked about you this afternoon.
今天下午,妈妈问起你了
She wanted to know where you were.
她想知道你在哪
I said you were still at school.
我说你还在学校
Did you go to the well?
你到井那去了吗?
Yes.
是的
Did you see him?
你看到了他了吗?
Because he doesn't know you.
当然,他不认识你
Papa's coming!
爸爸来了!
Papa, here's one.
爸爸,这有一个
- Papa, here's another one. - I'm coming.
- 这又有一个 - 我马上就来
It's bad.
这是坏的
How much you wanna bet?
这是好的,你赌多少?
Don't touch it.
不要碰
- It's good, isn't it? - Let's see.
- 这是好的,对吗? - 我看看
Yes, sir, that's a good mushroom.
没错,这是个很好的蘑菇
See?
看到了吗?
Who knows what it's called?
谁知道它叫什么?
- A brittlegill. - A flyswatter.
- 帕罗米塔 - 苍蝇拍
No, flyswatters are poisonous.
不对,苍蝇拍是有毒的
Look closely.
仔细看看他们
Trum... - Trumpet!
- 这是… - “耳朵”!
Very good.
非常好
You can tell by the brown color
你们根据褐色的外表 和弯曲的边缘
and these wavy edges.
来辨别他们
Papa, have you ever picked a poisonous mushroom?
你捡过有毒的蘑菇吗?
- No. You know why? - Why?
- 没有,知道为什么吗? - 为什么?
Because I always do Iike my grandfather told me.
我听爷爷的话
If you're not sure a mushroom's good, don't pick it.
如果你对一个蘑菇没把握, 就不要捡
Because if it's bad and you eat it,
因为如果是坏的, 你捡来吃了
it's your Iast mushroom, and your Iast everything else too.
它就是你最后的蘑菇,就死了
You two understand? - I do.
- 明白吗? - 我明白了
Grandfather wasn't crazy about eating them.
爷爷不太喜欢吃蘑菇
What he Iiked was Iooking for them,
他喜欢寻找蘑菇
even if it meant a full day's hike.
哪怕他得走一天
He never got tired.
他从来都不累
See that mountain?
看见那座山吗?
What he called "the mushroom garden" is up there.
他把它叫做蘑菇园
You know why? - Why?
- 知道为什么吗? - 为什么?
Because the best mushroom grows there - the chanterelle.
最好的蘑菇鸡油菌就生长在那
- Why don't we go? - It's too far.
- 我们可以去吗? - 太远了
We'd never make it with you two weaklings.
你们两个走不了那么远
We'II go some other day.
改天我们去
But first you have to promise
不过你们先要答应
never to tell your mother.
决不告诉妈妈
Look what we have here.
看看这是什么
A real devil.
真正的魔鬼
It smells so good.
闻起来很香
Sure, the young ones fool you,
它年轻的时候就骗的了你
but the older ones are a different story.
不过当它老了…
Look very closely.
仔细看看
Look at the color of the cap
看看蘑菇伞的颜色
and the black gills.
看看黑色的腮
Never forget, girls: This is the worst of all.
孩子们,千万记住,这是最坏的
The most poisonous.
最毒的
Whoever eats this hasn't got a chance in the world.
如果你吃了,解毒的方法都没有, 必死无疑
Fernando.
费尔南多!
See you Iater.
再见
- Good morning, Don Fernando. - Good morning.
- 你好,费尔南多先生 - 你好
We're getting a Iate start.
你晚了点
- You hit me! - I did not!
- 你打我! - 我没有
That's enough! Stop being so boisterous.
够了!玩够了!不要这么吵.
- Dummy! - Pig!
- 哑巴! - 猪!
Good Lord!
天哪!
What's all this ruckus?
吵死了!
- She started it. - That's enough!
- 她先动手的 - 够了!
She's Iying.
骗子
Come on. It's time to wash up for school.
好了,该洗漱上学了
First you get the brush wet.
先把毛刷弄湿
Okay.
好了
Then you rub it all over your face.
然后刷脸
Then you get it soapy.
再涂上肥皂
Now you rub it on your face.
然后刷到脸上
Okay.
好了
Now I shave off the Iittle hairs?
然后就刮小头发吗?
Yes, and then you put on some cologne.
是的,最后打上点古龙水
Mama, do you know what a spirit is?
妈妈,你知道什么是幽灵吗?
You don't know and I do.
你不知道,我知道
A spirit is a spirit.
幽灵就是幽灵
Are they good or bad?
他们是好的还是坏的?
With good Iittle girls, they're very good,
跟好姑娘在一起就是好的
but with bad girls, they're very bad.
但跟坏姑娘一起他们就是坏的
But you're always a good girl, aren't you?
不过你是好的,对吗
Give me a kiss.
亲一下
It's coming!
来了!
"Now neither malice nor hatred,
“既不是怨恨也不是仇恨
nor even the fear of change.
也不是变化的恐惧,
I only feel thirst,
我只感到口渴
a thirst for I know not what.
我不明白的口渴
Rivers of Iife, where have you gone?
生命之河,你去哪了?
Air, I need air.
空气,我需要空气
What do you see in the darkness that makes you silently tremble?
你在黑暗中看到的东西 会让你默默颤抖吗?
I see not but only stare Iike a blind man
我看到一个瞎子
facing straight into the sun.
看着太阳的脸
I shall fall where the fallen never rise."
我会落在落日不会升起的地方
"To... my...
“献给…我的…
dear...
亲爱的…
misanthrope."
厌世者”
Come here.
过来
What's wrong with you?
你怎么啦?
Come on, get up. Stop playing around.
快点起来,别玩了
He's not here anymore. He's gone.
他不在这了,他走了
Isabel, tell me what happened.
伊莎贝尔,你怎么啦
Milagros!
米拉格罗丝!
- Careful, you'II get burnt. - Isabel!
- 小心点,你是受伤的 - 伊莎贝尔!
Careful, Raquel.
小心点,雷可
What are you doing here, child?
你在这干什么?
Come on, Iet's go.
跟我来,走吧
Let's go home. Your father's back.
回家吧,你爸爸回来了
Let's go.
走吧
Come on, Iet's go.
快点,走吧
Where were you?
你去哪了?
Here.
拿着
Hello.
哈罗
Come in.
进来
- May l, sir? - Come in.
- 可以吗? - 带他进来
- He's here. - I'II be right there.
- 他来了 - 我马上就到
Ana, come here!
安娜,过来!
Get back!
回去吧!
Ana, what happened to you?
安娜,你怎么啦?
- Miguel, how is she? - Fine. Still a Iittle weak.
- 米古,他怎么啦? - 没事,还有点虚弱
She hardly sleeps. She won't eat or speak.
她不睡觉,不吃东西,不说话
Light bothers her.
光线让她不舒服
She Iooks our way but doesn't recognize us.
她看着我们,好像不认识我们
It's as if we didn't exist.
就好像我们不存在
Ana is still a very small child.
安娜还是个小孩子
She's under the effect of a powerful experience.
她受到一次强烈经历的影响
But she'II get over it.
她会熬过来的
Really, Miguel?
真的吗,米古?
Bit by bit she'II begin to forget.
慢慢的,她会忘掉的
The important thing is that your daughter's alive.
特里萨 重要的是你女儿还活着
She's alive.
她还活着
She's gone to sleep.
她睡着了
Don Miguel, she's asleep.
米古先生,她睡着了
Give her this medicine. The dose is right here.
给她服这个药
Yes, sir. I'II go right to the pharmacy.
好的,我这就去药房
She should eat. Something easy to digest.
她应该吃东西,容易消化的东西
Soup without too much fat,
汤不要油腻
a boiled egg.
水煮蛋
And you need rest too, Teresa,
还有你得休息,特里萨
as much as she does.
这也很重要
If anything happens, send Milagros for me. I'II come right away.
如果有什么事,让米拉格罗丝去找我
Yes, Miguel.
好的
Someone to whom I recently showed my glass beehive,
最近我向某人展示我的玻璃蜂巢
with its movement like the main gear wheel of a clock-
那个齿轮的运动就像时钟发条轮
Someone who saw the constant agitation of the honeycomb,
有人看见了仪表板的持久运动…
the mysterious, maddened commotion
永久的嗡嗡响
of the nurse bees over the nests,
蜂房神秘而疯狂的雄蜂…
the teeming bridges and stairways of wax,
桥梁和楼梯构成腊房
the invading spirals...
王后的侵略性的螺旋…
If you're his friend,
如果你是他的朋友
you can talk to him whenever you want.
你随时可以跟他说话
Just close your eyes
闭上眼睛
and call him.
呼唤他
"It's me, Ana. "
“是我,安娜.”